

Daniel Felipe Ordoñez Apraez

ELLIS Ph.D Student in Bioengineering and Robotics - M.Sc. Artificial Intelligence

CONTACT

Personal website

+39 351 9861722

in linkedin.com/in/danfoa

github.com/Danfoa

Google Scholar

Profile

Second year ELLIS Ph.D. student exploring the applications of group theory in robot modeling, control and design. My research strives to enhance robotic functionality through mathematically driven innovation. I have a specialized focus on the exploitation of structural/morphological symmetry groups in locomoting robotic and dynamical systems. Born in: 1995.

INTERESTS

Geometric Deep Learning

Group theory

Control theory

Differential Geometry

Dynamical System's theory

LANGUAGES

Spanish **English** German Italian

Mother Tongue C1 (TOEFL) Intermediate - B2 Basic

Programming







SOFTWARE









REFERENCES

Dr. Massimiliano Pontil

ITALIAN INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY Massimiliano.Pontil@iit.it

Dr. Mario Martin

Universitat Politècnica de CATALUNYA mmartin@cs.upc.edu

Dr. Claudio Semini

ITALIAN INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY claudio.semini@iit.it

EDUCATION

Oct 2022 Present

Genova / Edinburgh 💡

Italian Institute of Technology (IIT) - University of Genova **European Laboratory for Learning and Intelligent Systems (ELLIS)**

Ph.D. IN BIOENGINEERING AND ROBOTICS

Project: Study the modeling, control and design of symmetric dynamical systems with structural/morphological symmetry groups. Including:

- · Modeling equivariant dynamics with learned integral linear operators.
- Exploitation of harmonic analysis of structural groups for modeling/control.
- Optimal control of Markov Decision Processes with state-action symmetries.

Supervisors: Dr. Massimiliano Pontil (CSML), Dr. Claudio Semini (DLS), and Dr. Carlos Mastalli (RoMi).

2019-2021

Barcelona Spain **Q**

Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya - Barclona Tech

M.Sc. in Artificial Intelligence

Thesis: Learning to run naturally: guiding policies with the Spring-Loaded Inverted Pendulum. An approach to learn of realistic locomotion policies by exploiting sagittal reflectional symmetry and the passive dynamics bias.

· Part time researcher at the institute of Industrial Robotics and Informatics (IRI)

2013-2018

Bogota Colombia 💡

Universidad Nacional de Colombia

B.Sc. in Mechatronics Engineering - Major in Robotics Five year bachelor's program.

Exchange Semester: Technical University of Munich

EXPERIENCE

2021-2022 2019-2021

Barcelona Spain 9

Institut de Robòtica i Informàtica Industrial (IRI-CSIC)

ASSISTANT RESEARCHER STUDENT RESEARCHER

Research Projects: Learning realistic legged locomotion by imitating low order template passive models.

· Learning human hand synergies of motion with Variational Autoencoders

INVITE GmbH research center (TU Dortmund & Bayer AG)

2018-2019 2017-2018

Cologne Germany 9 JUNIOR RESEARCH ASSISTANT **ROBOTICS INTERN**

Research project: Manipulation of plastic bags using a two-arm robot with 3D vision and force feedback. (see presentation video)

· EP-Patent: Autonomous Drum and Inliner Handling

Publications - Patents

- * On discrete symmetries of robotics systems: A group-theoretic and data-driven analysis. Ordonez-Apraez, Daniel - Agudo, Antonio - Moreno, Francesc - Martin, Mario. Robotics Science and Systems RSS-2023
- An Adaptable Approach to Learn Realistic Legged Locomotion without Examples. Ordonez-Apraez, Daniel - Agudo, Antonio - Moreno, Francesc - Martin, Mario. 2022 International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)
- [Worshop] Morphological symmetries in robot learning. Ordonez-Apraez, Daniel Agudo, Antonio - Moreno, Francesc - Martin, Mario. RSS-2023 Workshop on Symmetries in Robot Learn-
- ❖ [Patent] Autonomous Drum and Inliner Handling. INVITE GmbH., Bayer A.G. Published European and US patent EP4112238A1/US2023009062A1.

Awards

Awarded COLFUTURO's scholarship/loan for higher education

2019 Top 1% score on the Colombian Saber-Pro national exam, which evaluates all students near graduation of a higher education's degree

2019 Selected to the Colombian COLFUTURO's recruitment of talent program and awarded scholarship/loan for higher education

University tuition exception 2015

OPEN-SOURCE PROJECTS

- MorphoSymm: Repository with tools for exploiting morphological/structural symmetry groups in robotics. Including:
 - * A library of symmetric robotic systems and the relevant group representations needed for transforming state/action spaces and proprioceptive/exteroceptive measurements.
 - ★ Tools for the construction of equivariant/invariant neural networks based on ESCNN.
 - # [In development] Tools for exploiting harmonic analysis of structural groups for modeling/control.
- * SLIP Control: Repository with tools for optimal control of the Spring-Loaded Inverted Pendulum (SLIP). A low order template model used for capturing the dynamics of legged locomotion. Including:
 - * An model predictive control based on the differential flatness of the actuated SLIP model.
 - * Tools for multi step/hops planning.
- * ROS driver for Robotiq 2F-85/140 Grippers: ROS packages enabling the control, visualization and simulation of the Robotiq 2 Fingers Adaptive Grippers model version C3.

Teaching and Invited Lectures

Feb 2023 Modern techniques of machine learning and control to robotics

Bogotá Seminar - Universidad Nacional de Colombia

Colombia V Lecture: On the role of symmetries in machine learning and control of robotic systems

Jan-Feb 2022 | Scene reconstruction and structure from Motion

Barcelona Spain 💡 Laboratory series of 3D-Vision course - Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona

Main Lecturer: Prof. Dr. Gloria Haro

Dec 2021 Introduction to AI for speech-language pathology students

Barcelona Bachelor in Speech-language pathology - Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona

Spain ♥ Higher cognitive functions seminar series. Main Lecturer: Prof. Paula Resina

Mar-Dec 2016 | Engineering faculty tutor

Bogotá Universidad Nacional de Colombia

Colombia Courses tutored: - Data structures and algorithms - Numerical methods - Control theory - Object-oriented

programming - Basic programming

Presentations

Oct 2023 Symmetries in robot modeling and control

Berkley Hybrid Robotics Laboratory seminar series. University of California, Berkeley

Invited seminar lecture (Slides)

July 2023 Morphological symmetries in robot learning

Daegu Workshop on Symmetries in Robot Learning (RSS-2023)

Korea ♥ Workshop presentation: youtu.be/E2l16T0biu4

May 2023 [Spotlight] Morphological symmetries in robot learning

London Worshop Effective Representations, Abstractions, and Priors for Robot Learning (ICRA-2023)

Workshop presentation: youtu.be/vxTKCbNNU8M

Dec 2021 An Adaptable Approach to Learn Realistic Legged Locomotion without Examples

Barcelona Poster at Deep Learning Barcelona Symposium

Spain ♥

UK 🗣

US 💡